# YAW SARFO MARFO

# **Business & Tech Consultant**

# Contact

# (+233) 540-617-952



yawsarfomarfo@gmail.com



GA-392-3996, Diabase ST



linkedin.com/in/yawsafomarfo



# Education

- Certification in Fashion
   Design & Illustrations,
   Riohs College of Design 2024
- 120 Hour TEFL Certification in Teaching English, TEFL Professional Institute-2024
- Professional Certificate in Fullstack Web & Mobile
   Development
   OpenLabs Ghana, NIIT -2022
- Professional Certificate in Python Programming
   OpenLabs Ghana, NIIT -2022
- Executive Masters in Alternative Disputes
   Resolution, Institute of Paralegal Training and Leadership Studies --2016
- Bachelor of Science in Administration, Accounting
   Option, University of Ghana
   --2015
- WASSCE, Business Studies,
   Sunyani Senior High --2011

# Profile

Dedicated technical consultant with diverse operational experience in both IT development and business intelligence analysis. Several years of experience creating customized solutions to address specific customer requirements, improve overall productivity, and dramatically increase efficiency. Extensive IT and network experience including building a complete system architecture from the ground up to meet specific client requirements. Safo is a versatile technology consultant with a passion for leadership, problem solving, and producing valuable insights for clients utilizing data and new technologies while fostering innovation, collaboration and the development of peers.

# Professional Experience

# **MOBILE & ELECTRONIC BANKING & LOAN OFFICER**

JUN 2020 –To Date

Kantanka Financial Cooperative Society - Achimota, GR

- Reviewing, authorizing and recommending loans for approval. Assessing the risk of Loan applicants.
- Coordinating with our mobile bankers to enabling customers to access banking services easily, quickly and conveniently anytime, anywhere.
- Lead and oversee the Mobile Banking department, responsible for providing seamless and secure electronic banking services to customers.
- Collaborate with cross-functional teams, including IT, operations, and marketing, to ensure smooth integration and operation of electronic banking systems.

# **PROGRAMMER & NETWORK CONSULTANT**

**JUNE 2019** 

Blackmind Technology - Accra, GR

--To Date

- Programming/Development: Develop and maintain software applications and solutions using various programming languages and frameworks. Collaborate with cross-functional teams to design, code, test, debug, and deploy software solutions that meet client requirements. Ensure highquality code by following best practices and coding standards.
- Network Design and Implementation: Design and implement network infrastructure for clients, including LAN, WAN, and Wireless networks. Analyze client requirements and develop network architecture plans to optimize performance, security, and scalability. Configure and install network devices, such as routers, switches, firewalls, and wireless access points.
- Network Security: Assess client network vulnerabilities and implement appropriate security measures to protect against unauthorized access, data breaches, and other threats.
- Troubleshooting and Technical Support: Provide technical support to clients for network and software-related issues.

# Time Management Integrity Professionalism Organization Curiosity Team Work Discipline Excellence

People-Cantered • • • • • •

# IT Proficiency

- JavaScript
- HTML 5
- CSS 4
- Bootstrap 5
- React JS Library
- JQuery Library
- Python Language
- Django Framework
- Node.Js Framework
- Next.Js Framework
- Firebase Database
- MySQL database
- DeVops Tools
- Computer Networking
- Sage Accounting Software
- QuickBooks Accounting Software
- Microsoft Word
- Microsoft Excel
- Microsoft PowerPoint
- Social Media Tools
- AWS & Cloud Computing

#### SUPERVISOR & REP-YOUTH IN AFFORESTATION

Forestry Commission - Sunyani Municipal, BA

JUL 2019 To NOV 2019

- Supervises tree pruning, trimming and cutting activities.
- Supervises the use of hand and power saws, rope pulleys, cherry picker and other equipment
- Recommends schedules of tree preventive maintenance
- Prepare routine reports on work activities
- Supervises tree planting and transplanting
- Determine appropriate location for new trees.

#### **REGIONAL FINANCIAL CONTROLLER**

**MAY 2018** 

Kristo Asafo Mission - Bono & Ahafo Region

--To Date

- Manage day-to-day administrative operations, ensuring smooth functioning of the office.
- Coordinate and schedule appointments, meetings, and travel arrangements for senior management.
- Maintain records and databases, including employee files, project documentation, and financial records.
- Process and manage paperwork, including invoices, purchase orders, and contracts.
- Prepare and distribute internal communications, memos, and reports as required.

# **FINANCE OFFICER**

**SEP 2017** 

WASP Company Ltd - Greater Accra Region

To DEC 2017

- Preparing payroll, invoices, requisitions, stock taking, tax computations, budgets and other related financial transactions
- Tracking the company's financial status and performance to identify areas for potential improvement
- Reviewing financial data; Prepare Weekly, Monthly and Annual reports
- Presenting financial reports to Board Members, Stakeholders, Executives, and Clients in formal meetings

#### **ADMINISTRATOR**

APR 2017

Sanyakwa Construction Company Ltd - Accra, GR

To JUL 2017

- Ensuring strict confidentiality regarding all business and client matters.
- Authoring, maintaining, and distributing a myriad of financial and production reports including cash flow reports, invoices, purchase orders, contracts, vendor, and job files.
- Ensuring production agendas remained on track and within projected guidelines.
- Studying, inspecting and assessing; budgets, balance sheets and other related financial statements and records.

#### Certification/Awards

#### TEFL Certification

Certification in English Teaching, **TEFL Professional Development Institute** 

#### Executive Masters

Alternative Disputes Resolution, IPLS

#### Undergraduate Degree

BSc in Administration, University of Ghana Business School

#### Professional Certificate

Fullstack Web & Mobile Development, **OpenLabs Ghana** 

#### Professional Certificate

Python programming, **OpenLabs Ghana** 

#### Cloud Computing

Trending Technologies by Industry Experts, OpenLabs | NIIT | Skill Africa Ltd

#### Cyber Security

Trending Technologies by Industry Experts, OpenLabs | NIIT | Skill Africa Ltd

#### Data Analysis With Excel

Trending Technologies by Industry Experts, OpenLabs | NIIT | Skill Africa Ltd

# Grow Your Business Using Instagram

Trending Technologies by Industry Experts, OpenLabs | NIIT | Skill Africa Ltd

# • Most Discipline Student

Youth of Kristo Asafo, University of Ghana Branch

#### WASSCE Certificate

Business Studies, Sunyani Senior High

# • Kantanka Excellence Awards

Excellence in WASSCE Examination

#### • Kantanka Excellence Awards

**Excellence in BECE Examination** 

# Second In Command

Ghana Army Cadet Corps, Sunyani Senior High School

# President

Ghana National Association of Business Students, Sunyani Senior High

# Main House Prefect

P D Quartey House, Sunyani Senior High

# Professional Experience

#### **AUDIT ASSISTANT**

FEB 2017 To MAY 2017

PKF Ghana (Accounting, Audit & Business Advisory) - Accra, GR

- Executing checks on the accuracy of accounting systems and procedures.
- Verifying and inspecting accounts receivable and payable ledgers and general ledger for its accuracy.
- Checking, inspecting and reconciling bank deposits and payments.
- Studying, inspecting and assessing; budgets, balance sheets and other related financial statements and records.
- Checking and verifying accounting books and records are in conformity with industry practices and corporate policies.

#### **CEO & BUSINESS CONSULTANT**

**FEB 2017** 

Answers Business Services (Registrations & Consultancy) – Accra, GR --To DATE

- Formulating policies and planning recommendations to the Board
- Deciding and guiding courses of action in operations by staff
- Ensuring staff and Board have sufficient and up-to-date information
- Interfacing between organization and community
- Overseeing operations and Implementing plans

# DATA ENTRY, WELFARE AND CLIENT SERVICES

SEP 2015

Ghana Revenue Authority - Accra, GR

To AUG 2016

- Helping clients in filing their tax returns.
- Advising clients on tax payments and other formalities.
- Handling the Clients queries related to tax payment
- Registration of tax payers by capturing their data through the electronic system and managing their tax database.

# **ADMINISTARTIVE ASSISTANT & MEDIATOR**

JUN 2015

Mediation Centre, Legal Aid Commission -Sunyani, BA

To AUG 2015

- Performing general clerical duties to include but not limited to: photocopying, mail distribution and filing.
- Assisting the senior accountant with various tasks, including preparing budgets, records, and statements
- Creating and modifying various documents using Microsoft Office.
- Coordinating meetings and conference calls as needed or anticipated.
- Assisting in the settlement of Disputes presented by Clients.

# Certification/Awards

#### Value Creation Submit

Building a Sure Future Today, Tigo & SRC Campus Storm

# What The Employers Need

Employment, Performance, Marketing, Competition; Turning Page & Vodafone

#### National Service

E-government Department , **Ghana Revenue Authority** 

# Mission Statement

My mission is to help customers achieve their business objectives by providing innovative, best-inclass consulting, IT solutions and services. To make it a joy for all stakeholders to work with me.

I wish serve as a leader, live a balanced life, and apply ethical principles to make a significant difference

#### Hobbies

- Building Machines and Researching on Technology Trends
- Writing Programming Codes,
   Reading books, Creative
   Writing and Teaching,
- Drumming and Mixing of Sounds (Dics Jockey), Creative Drawing
- Public Presentation, Inspiring
   People and Directing Event
   Activities
- Researching on Financials & Brainstorming on Business
   Development

# Professional Experience

# **REGIONAL COORDINATOR**

Technology in Ghana Co Ltd -Brong Ahafo Region

APR 2014 To DEC 2015

- Maintaining administrative workflow by studying methods; implementing cost reductions; developing reporting procedures.
- Developing administrative staff by providing information, educational opportunities, and coaching.
- Maintaining suggestion system by directing and controlling administrative technical aspects in accordance with management directives.

#### **TREASURER**

JAN 2014

Youth of Kristo Asafo -University of Ghana Branch

To DEC 2014

- General financial oversight
- Preparing and monitoring budgets and maintains accurate financial records
- Funding, fundraising and sale of union souvenirs
- Financial reporting
- Banking, book-keeping and record-keeping

#### Referees

# Mr. Francis Kudjo Kudjordjie

- General Manager,
- Kantanka Automobile Limited
- Greater, Accra
- Mob. N#: +233-546-066-995
- kojokujoji@gmail.com

# Ms. Mary Mould

- Principal Revenue Officer,
- Ghana Revenue Authority,
- E-Government Department,
- Accra, Greater Accra,
- Mob. N#: +233-20 817 4660.

# Mr. Collins Kwadwo Safo, CGMA ACMA CA

- Internal Auditor
- CAGD Regional Directorate
- Sunyani, Bono Region
- Mob. N#: +233 24 207 0322
- Collins.safo@cagd.gov.gh